- "Previously on The Mentalist..."
- "Who's that?"
Bob Kirkland, Homeland Security.
- Do I know you?
- No, but I know you.
Get me everything.
"Jane made a lot of Red John
connections here."
This is good.
- "Why is this a Homeland Security issue?"
- "It's complicated."
- Agent Lisbon, Jane, CBI.
- Sorry.
F.B.I. Personnel only.
We don't want to be here, either
but we were invited.
Could you tell agent Reede Smith
that we're here as requested?
What do you think
Smith wants?
I don't know.
What do you think?
Every time we go to see one of these
Red John suspects I get edgy.
- Really? Can't tell.
- Really?
Jane, Lisbon.
Thanks for coming.
Miss this?
Who could say no?
How can we be of help,
agent Smith?
We caught a body.
I thought it might interest you.
- And why would you say that?
- You tell me.
- This is Benjamin Marx.
- The guy you buried alive.
Excuse me.
The killer I buried alive.
And I did let him out...
eventually.
Not bad.
That's a tough I.D.
considering most of his
face is burnt off.
What do you think
happened to him?
You're the F.B.I.
I'm sure you have the answers already.
Okay.
Tell me what I've come up with.
Well, the first thing you'd notice
is that he was tortured...
With fire and whatever it is people use
to cut someone's thumbs off.
And what do I think
he was tortured for?
Well, your guess would be
sadistic pleasure, but you'd be wrong
more likely he was tortured
for information...
Information that he didn't have.
- How do you know he didn't have it?
- Because if he had it
the killer would only have had
to burn off half his face.
What else do I think?
Well, whoever did the torturing
took their time
so you would reason that they
had somewhere private to do it.
- Right.
- And I'm sure you saw
the sticky stuff on the leg of the victim
probably sent it off to the lab.
And in three days they'll tell you
that it's pine sap, which makes sense
because there's a broken pine needle
wedged into the sole of his shoe.
- Yeah, I see.
- Eventually you'd come to the conclusion
that he was kept
in the woods someplace
before he was killed
and dumped here.
Nice.
Why are we here, agent Smith?
Marx was out on bail
while he stood trial.
Things were looking good
for him, too.
I mean, you tortured him into a confession
so a little good lawyering
a little luck, and he could walk.
Bet that really chapped
your hide, huh, Jane?
Not at all.
That's the best theory
the F.B.I. can come up with?
That Jane killed Benjamin Marx
and burned his face off?
We're exploring every angle.
He's an angle.
Listen. If I wanted
to kill Benjamin Marx
I would have done it
the first time.
He was a sociopath that stole
from widows and orphans
and he got what he deserved.
But I didn't do it.
- We'll see.
- Yes, we will.
Thanks for coming.
- What's going on, Jane?
- Nothing.
- Tell me.
- I said it's nothing.
It's never nothing with you.
- Do you think Smith is Red John?
- Possibly.
Well, if he isn't Red John,
he's an idiot
for thinking you could have anything to do
with Marx's death.
He's not completely wrong.
I mean, I didn't kill Benjamin Marx
but I might have gotten him killed.
Okay, no more secrets.
Spill it now.
I was concerned with security when I was
working my list of Red John suspects.
- Obsessively secretive.
- Yeah, well, you say "tomato"
but I knew there were people
that needed that information.
So I planted what you would call
misinformation on my crime board.
So whoever saw your crime board got
the list of the seven Red John suspects.
But they would be the wrong suspects.
Exactly. And it worked.
- Someone broke into my office.
- How do you know?
Well, I set a trap,
and it was sprung.
Now this person has a fake list
of Red John suspects
and Benjamin Marx
was on that list.
So somebody is torturing and killing
the people on your fake list.
Whoa, whoa.
Not necessarily.
Someone tortured and killed
one person from my list.
But theoretically, his death
could be about anything.
He wasn't a nice man.
I am trying to wrap
my mind around this.
You put the lives of seven
innocent people in danger.
No. None of them are innocent.
Marx defrauded
hundreds of people...
then he brutally murdered
someone to cover it up.
I assure you, Lisbon...
all of these men
are very bad.
They just don't happen
to be Red John.
Do you think the real Red John
could have broken in here
and killed Marx?
Well, Red John is the only person besides
us that knows the real list of suspects
so he is the only person that
has no motive to do this.
- Then who broke in here?
- I don't know.
Someone with easy access,
a lot of resources and power.
The F.B.I.
they've been wanting to get their hands
on the Red John case for a while.
They were not happy when
Homeland Security took over.
True.
You know, I've always suspected
the F.B.I. are watching me. Personally.
As paranoid as it sounds it would explain
how they got the Marx case.
But why would they do this to him?
And how do we proceed?
I can't just go to the F.B.I. and ask them
if they killed Marx.
If the F.B.I. has been
watching me
I'll bet that someone
very high up in the CBI
authorized it,
or at least went along with it.
- I need to talk to them.
- Bertram.
But you obviously can't ask him.
Madeleine Hightower then.
Hightower? She hasn't run
the CBI in three years.
What kind of information do you
think she still has access to?
And if so, why would she
share it with you?
Well, Red John tried to kill her.
- She's gonna want to help me.
- Unless she blames you.
- I'm gonna call her.
- Fine.
Oh. What do you have
planned for the day?
You don't officially have a case,
do you? You can relax.
Get a massage,
mani/pedi.
No.
I have to go
and offer protection
to the six people on your list,
which you are going to give me.
I was hoping
you'd opt for the massage.
Oh, I can't believe it.
Finally got him back to sleep.
Good job, Mr. Rigsby.
And we don't have to leave for work
for another hour.
What are we gonna do
to pass the time?
Well, I don't know,
Mrs. Rigsby.
- Oh... Don't.
- Oh...
- It's Lisbon.
- She can wait 10 minutes.
- Lisbon.
- It must be important. You should get it.
Morning, boss.
You and Rigsby take these four.
I'll take Haibach and Lee.
Isn't Haibach the guy
from the panzer case
with all the photos
of the little girls?
Yeah. I've dealt
with him once before
so maybe he'll be more likely
to come with me.
Rape charges, drug charges
human trafficking charges.
Really?
We're gonna help these guys?
That's the job.
We don't get to pick and choose.
We need to warn these men
that their lives are in danger
and offer them protection.
Now get on it.
And I was watching her
brush her teeth this morning
and she does the full two minutes
just like the dentist says.
The wrong person,
that could be really annoying
but today I just thought, cool.
I'm gonna be spending the rest of my life
with those really good teeth, you know?
Nope.
My point is, marriage is
even better than I thought.
Except...
well... it's not a big deal.
It's only been three days.
It's sort of funny, really.
We haven't done it yet.
As a married couple.
What about at the hotel?
After the wedding. I got you that carriage.
Yeah, we passed out.
It was a very emotionally
draining day.
- Plus we drank too much.
- Right.
Then we had to work
the next day.
And since then, Sara's
at a conference in L.A.
so we've had ben every day,
morning and night.
You know, I read
a study on the internet.
It said women lose interest in sex
almost immediately after marriage.
- It's Darwinian.
- Nah, not Grace.
She's always been super into...
My point is, I don't believe it.
It's not true.
I'm just telling you
what the internet said.
Rick Dort? CBI.
Open up.
Anyone can say anything on the internet.
Doesn't mean it's true.
- Yeah?
- Mr. Dort?
Agents Rigsby and Cho from the CBI.
We want to talk to you about...
Hands in the air,
or I'll shoot you in the head.
Hey, man, don't shoot.
We have reason to believe
your life's in danger.
We came to offer
police protection.
- What?
- Your life is in danger.
It is?
You're not here about
the meth... other thing?
The meh... other thing?
There is no other thing.
- Slip of the tongue.
- Get out of the pool.
Hey, Grace.
You look a little peaked.
I found out why you haven't been able
to get in touch with Hightower.
- What is it? Tell me.
- I spoke to her aunt
and she said Hightower
and the kids had an accident.
- They're dead.
- What? When?
Two weeks ago on vacation
in Mexico. They drowned.
How come we didn't hear
about it sooner?
It's very strange.
Apparently, they never
found the bodies
and authorities have called off
the search and rescue.
What did you say
her aunt's name was?
Ruby. Ruby Hightower.
Yeah, well, I'm gonna
need an address.
I need to send her some flowers.
That's terrible.
- "This is Bob Kirkland."
- Kirkland.
This is agent Reede Smith, F.B.I.
What can I do for you, Smith?
"I think it's what I can do for you."
My superiors asked that I fill you in
on a case I'm working.
- It involves Patrick Jane.
- I'm listening.
"It's a murder/kidnapping thing."
"Vic's a guy named Benjamin Marx.
Jane dealt with him before."
Used some... shall we say
over-the-top techniques
to get Marx to confess?
That sounds about right.
"Marx was on trial,
could have gone free."
Frankly, I like Jane for it.
He's got a vigilante beef
with Red John.
Maybe this is his thing.
I think you might be on to something.
- Nice work.
- "Thanks."
- And, Smith? Keep me in the loop.
- Yes, sir.
- Yes?
- Mrs. Hightower?
I'm so sorry for your loss.
I used to work with
your niece Madeleine
and, uh, well, I was hoping
that maybe we could talk.
These are for you.
Oh, please come in.
Thank you. They're very nice.
When was the last time
you saw your niece?
A few weeks ago, right before
they went on vacation.
They made a point
to come and see me.
At least I got a chance
to say good-bye.
Yeah, well, there...
there's that.
- What is it?
- Oh, it's just, uh...
I just wish that there was
some way I could...
Let her know
how I feel.
There is.
My neighbor is very good
with the computer.
He set up a private memorial site
on the internet
just for friends and family.
I'd love to see that.
- Okay, here you go.
- Oh, do you mind?
I'm not very good
with computers.
Sure. Just say
what you need to say.
Write this.
In death...
you have found new life...
and I want to shout it
from the mountaintops.
I know in my heart
dearest Madeleine...
that when sunset comes
I will find you
waiting for me...
in the heavenly gardens.
Love, Patrick.
Oh... That was, um...
that's lovely.
Very poetical.
Thank you.
Feels a lot better.
- I should... I should go.
- Oh, you poor lamb.
You were a little sweet
on her, weren't you?
No. I remember you.
Talk to my lawyer.
Mr. Haibach.
It's not what you think.
Just hear me out.
I think you've wanted to pin
something on me for a long time.
- I won't be your patsy, Ms. Lisbon.
- It's agent Lisbon.
And we have reason to believe
that your life is in danger.
I am here to offer you
police protection.
So if I go with you,
nothing bad will happen to me?
Sounds like police state
trickery, agent Lisbon.
The Stasi would be proud.
I am legally and morally bound
to inform you that...
Please don't try to stake out
the moral high ground here.
If you had your way, I'd be in jail
for a crime I didn't commit.
I think I'll take my chances.
"How's it going, Jane?"
- I just visited with Hightower's aunt.
- "That's so sad."
Did you find anything out?
I mean, do you think Red John
had anything to do with it.
I don't think so.
Not his M.O.
- So you think it's just an accident?
- Looks like it.
How's the roundup going?
Haibach wouldn't come with me.
I think he's hiding something.
Well, a guy like that
probably takes issue with lady police.
"Ladies in general."
Uh, you're right. You know what?
I'll send Cho and Rigsby.
Or not. Would the world really miss him
if something happened?
And that's the difference
between you and me.
"And good-bye."
If you are from CBI, I'm...
What happened?
We found the door open
blood and beer bottle on the floor.
No Haibach.
Rigsby's canvassing the neighbors.
This is bad.
Not really.
Confirms the theory that someone is going
through my list trying to find Red John.
Haibach has been abducted
and he's probably gonna be tortured to death.
Yeah, he's in for a rough night.
And we have to tell Smith
and the F.B.I.
that he's been taken and that
it's connected to the Marx case.
- No, we don't.
- We can't lie.
We do it all the time.
He's gonna put it together eventually
and it'll be worse.
Okay, fine. Tell him.
But do not mention the list.
Just tell him that someone else connected
to an old case of ours has gone missing.
Agreed.
What do we do now?
I will have the answer
for that very soon.
I have black, milk...
and milk and sugar.
I'll take whatever
you don't want.
- You always this thorough?
- I like to cover all my bases.
Milk and sugar.
Thanks.
So you said you got
something for me?
There's been an interesting development
in that case I was telling you about.
Looks like another man's gone missing
that's connected with Jane.
- A Richard Haibach.
- That is interesting.
Thank you.
Look, it's none
of my business, but...
can I ask what the deal is
with you and Jane?
- Long story.
- Whatever.
I'm not looking to pry.
I like that.
I've done some research on you.
- On me?
- Yeah. You're a good agent.
Real straight shooter.
Why would you research me?
I have some other business
I wanna discuss with you.
- Delicate business.
- Okay. Shoot.
Tiger tiger.
What, are you messing with me?
What... what is that? "Tiger tiger"?
- You really don't know?
- Know what?
Nothing. That's a test.
Okay.
I'm totally in the dark here.
You want to fill me in?
While investigating Red John
Homeland Security's begun to suspect
the existence of a powerful
secret organization
within California
law enforcement.
Police, CBI, D.O.J.
Strictly high-level, we think.
- What do they do?
- They do dirt.
They protect each other
with major cover-ups
get away with murder.
What's the tiger thing?
We think that's the password.
Spooky.
- Is Red John a member?
- It's too soon to tell.
What about Jane?
We're just starting
to put this thing together.
We're looking for partners
within the F.B.I.
lower level guys that...
we're sure we can trust.
That's me.
Happy to help.
Thank you.
I'll be in touch.
Thanks for the coffee.
Hello, Patrick.
Madeleine.
Thank you for coming.
Tea?
Yes, please.
Just so we're clear
I have a gun pointed
under the table.
And it's pointed
at something important.
Fair enough.
- How are the kids?
- They're safe.
That's all you need to know.
Your aunt is a delight.
Wonderful actress.
I had to do what was best for me
and my kids.
I knew that Red John was cleaning house
after Lorelei Martins was killed.
- I did not want to be next.
- No, I got it.
He's already tried
to kill you once.
It's not something you ever
really get over.
So what's so damn important
you had to bring me out of hiding?
I'm getting close to catching Red John
and I need your help.
I'm not putting my family in danger
to help you.
Besides, I've been out of law enforcement
for three years.
How can I help you?
I don't know anything.
Really?
Because I think you've been holding
something back for a very long time.
Yeah, there it is.
I'm right.
The F.B.I....
They've been watching me,
haven't they?
Please, I wouldn't be here
if it weren't important.
Tell me.
Well, I guess there's no reason
not to tell you now.
But obviously you did not
hear this from me.
When Minnelli was chief
of the CBI
He struck a deal with F.B.I.
Director Schultz.
- What did Schultz want?
- She wanted reports.
On you.
Minnelli provided them.
When Minnelli retired,
that became a part of my job.
But the intel wasn't exactly
going to the F.B.I.
I found out that Schultz was passing it on
to Homeland Security.
- Bob Kirkland?
- Yes.
- Why?
- He thought you were Red John.
Of course.
How long have Homeland Security
been watching me?
Eight, nine years.
I did what I thought was best at the time.
- Don't expect me to apologize.
- No, no, I won't.
Jane.
You cannot tell anyone you saw me.
Even Lisbon.
And I won't.
I meant what I said.
I'm gonna kill Red John
and you're gonna get your life back.
I hope so.
So what's next?
Well, I'm gonna go see
Bob Kirkland.
What I'm looking for is an open
and honest dialogue.
100% transparency.
I don't know what you want from me.
I didn't do anything wrong.
Maybe not yet.
But... That room
in your basement.
Come on.
You are a depraved man.
At minimum, a pedophile.
But frankly, that's not
why we're here.
Why then?
Please just tell me... Why.
I brought you here
to ask you some questions.
Anything. I'll...I'll tell you anything.
All right then.
Tell me...
Do you recognize me?
Have you seen me before?
No... I don't think so.
Okay, we'll come back to that.
Next question.
What?
- Are you Red John?
- What?
Are you... Red John?
No...
- Are you Red John?!
- No!
Agent Kirkland? Hey...
- Jane, what are you doing here?
- Can I have a quick word?
It's nothing private.
Your friends can stay.
I'll catch up, guys.
I have a pet theory
I was hoping you could confirm or Deny.
I'll see what I can do.
Has Homeland Security been
investigating me?
Yes.
I'm surprised you're
allowed to tell me that.
I mean, you guys are usually
so cloak and dagger.
Well, it's no secret that Homeland Security
has the Red John case.
Yeah, your name has come up
in various ways.
Right. So then did you guys
break into my office
- and steal my list of suspects?
- Absolutely not.
No? Why not?
Because we don't care
who you think Red John is.
We have the case.
Point taken.
Thanks for your time.
That's it?
Yeah. I just wanted to make sure
you weren't on a wild goose chase
because whoever it was
that broke into my office
they stole a fake list
of suspects.
- Well played.
- Thank you. I thought so.
- Maybe you should come work for us.
- Maybe not.
You need a ride somewhere?
No, I'm...I'm good, thanks.
Well, we should talk some more.
Get in the car.
- Do I have a choice?
- No.
By all means...
Let's talk some more.
Let me see your phone.
Hey, you don't have to do this.
I actually want to talk to you.
Just hand me the phone.
Seatbelt, please.
- Hey, have you guys heard from Jane?
- Nope.
I haven't seen him
since yesterday morning.
His phone just keeps on
going straight to voicemail.
Can you ping it for me?
- Sure. It'll take me a little while.
- Thanks. It's probably nothing.
And here we are.
Keep moving.
Oh, I love what you've done
with the place.
Come on, I'll give you
the 10-cent tour.
Help me... Please.
- Richard Haibach, Patrick Jane.
- Help me.
I just wanted you to see the face of the man
who got you into this mess.
It's a funny story, actually...
A comedy of errors.
Please let me go.
- No.
- Please.
But don't worry.
Jane'll get his, too.
So, let's talk about that real list
of Red John suspects.
I couldn't get a hit on Jane's phone.
Wherever he is, he has no cell service.
That's probably him now.
This is Lisbon.
"Hello, Lisbon.
Do you know who this is?"
Yes.
I thought you were dead.
- I met with Jane yesterday.
- He didn't say.
"I asked him not to tell you"
but I think I might have
gotten him into trouble.
- I've been trying to call him all day.
- Me, too.
"I gave him some
information yesterday."
Did he say anything to you
about who he was going to see?
- No. Should he have?
- "Yes."
"We need to talk."
I think I might have caused Jane
to do something very dumb.
Funny thing about the list.
I'd... Rather not share it with you.
I get it. It's been your pet project
for a long time.
Mine, too.
But you will share it with me.
What if I just give you
one name to start?
Robert Kirkland.
Interesting.
Makes sense, actually.
But it doesn't really help me
with my cause, though, does it?
No, I suppose not.
I was wrong about you.
You're not Red John.
You're hunting him, same as me.
Not exactly the same.
I'm willing to kill seven people
to get the job done.
- Touché.
- Why aren't you?
'Cause that would
make me a murderer.
You're planning on murdering Red John.
That doesn't make any sense.
Okay, so we...we both have
different approaches
but the important thing here
is that we share a common goal.
We can help each other
if we work together.
I'm not interested in working together
and I doubt you are, either.
We both want our revenge
and only one of us is going to get it.
Robert Kirkland.
- I know I should be surprised, but...
- But he's a creepy guy, that's why.
Where would he take Jane?
Probably the same place
he took Benjamin Marx.
Jane saw a pine needle
in Marx's shoe.
It was like he'd walked through
a pine forest before he was killed.
Lots of pine needles
in northern California.
Kirkland would be
keeping up appearances.
He'd be going to the office
every day, so...
pine forest within a hundred-mile
radius of Sacramento?
Sure, sure.
If that's all we got.
"Hey, boss."
Van Pelt, I need you
to run something for me.
Properties or businesses
owned by Robert Kirkland
"within 100 miles of the capitol...
in close proximity to a pine forest."
- Robert Kirkland?
- It's a long story.
Nothing for Robert Kirkland
within a hundred miles.
But there's a Michael Kirkland.
Owns a cabin up near
El Dorado state park.
- Oh, is he a relative?
- I don't know. I can check.
- All right, text me the address.
- "Sure."
We should call local
authorities for backup.
No. No. No cops.
Nobody can know about me.
Please.
Okay. How do we do this?
That's how.
- Do you have siblings, Jane?
- No.
I had a twin brother...
Michael.
We were very close
growing up.
I hear that's a strong bond.
And our father was
a sadistic drunk.
He beat the crap out of us
and our mother.
Beat her till she couldn't
take it anymore.
- She left?
- With a razor blade.
After that
it was just me and Michael.
I was all he had.
- You were the stronger one.
- Yeah.
I grew up. I got away.
But Michael couldn't do it.
He stayed at home and watched
our father drink himself to death.
The apple doesn't fall
far from the tree.
You're right.
Michael turned to the bottle
drank like his life depended on it.
I paid for treatments.
I took him to meetings.
- Nothing worked.
- Until?
Until one day he met someone
a man who could help him.
More than a man.
A savior.
Yeah. Red John.
He only asked for a few
simple things in return.
Devotion and sacrifice.
Michael drifted
further and further away
until one day he was gone.
I never saw him again.
You think Red John
killed your brother.
Yes.
I never found him
but in my heart, I know.
Look at me blab.
I... You're not my therapist.
I didn't bring you here to talk.
Please tell me
who the suspects are.
No.
Have it your way.
You understand, I'm gonna
have to torture you.
You don't seem like someone
who deals well with physical pain.
Not particularly.
- A name then.
- I can't do it.
Fine.
God!
Okay, okay, okay.
You... You... you have to understand
this is hard for me... emotionally.
I've never said any of these
names out loud to anyone.
A name.
Turtmee.
First name... Don.
Don Turtmee?
"Don't hurt me."
You got me.
Why, I oughta...
Put your hands in the air!
Keep 'em where we can see 'em!
Jane, you all right?
Oh, never better.
I'm just fine. Dandy.
Thanks to us. You were foolish
to come here alone.
You taking pleasure in this?
Don't get me wrong.
- You are a pain in the ass.
- Well, thank you.
But I wouldn't want anything
bad to happen to you
especially when it would be my fault.
Well, I'm sure your conscience
is clear now.
It is. Now leave me alone.
Next time I hear from you
you better be telling me Red John is dead.
Deal.
That is a deal.
Thank you, Madeleine.
You're welcome, Patrick.
Good luck.
Lisbon...
- You good here?
- Yeah.
You can call
for that backup now.
You'll pay for this!
I won't forget!
This is on you!
You sure you're all right?
The list is down to five names.
That is a very manageable number.
Somehow that doesn't
reassure me.
We're in the home stretch, Lisbon.
Hey guys. So...
looks like I got it
wrong about you.
Yeah. Looks like you did.
Ah, it's all right.
We all make mistakes.
I mean, a...
a Homeland Security agent?
Who would have thought, right?
Not me.
It's gonna be a jurisdictional
cluster-bomb.
But we'll book him first
at county.
In a few days he'll get transferred
to a federal detention center.
- I'd like to talk to him for a sec.
- Sure. Hey, Jane.
- No hard feelings, huh?
- No. No hard feelings.
Lisbon.
If you have anything else to say
now would be the time.
Oh, I might know some things.
But this isn't the best place to talk.
- Come see me sometime.
- I will.
- Are you gonna finish this thing?
- Yes.
- Hey.
- Hey. Lisbon called.
They're not coming back
into the office tonight.
- Okay.
- You can probably go, too.
- There's nobody else here.
- Sure.
- Did you change?
- What, this old thing?
Wait. What's this?
It looks like
a hotel room key.
- Wait. You didn't, did you?
- I did. The honeymoon suite.
Mrs. Capello
is watching Ben.
That's amazing.
Thank you.
- You know, I was beginning to think...
- I know what you thought.
- And am I crazy?
- Yes.
You shouldn't think
so much, Wayne.
Come on.
Don't mind me.
Let me speak to him.
What's going on?
What are you doing here?
You hit the nail on the head, Bob.
About what?
There is a powerful organization
within law enforcement.
But it's a lot bigger
than you thought.
It's not just the big boys, either.
They even let lower level
guys like me in.
I know what you're doing.
We've had our eye on you
for a long time.
We just want to help.
It's what we do.
Help me how?
Listen to me closely.
That's the address
of a safe house.
It's 2 miles due east of here.
When you get there,
someone will contact you
get you some money,
I.D., clothes.
I don't believe you.
Come on, Bob.
Get out of the van.
- Start running.
- Just do it here.
Actually, I'd prefer it if you Ran.
You know... Protocol.
Agent Kirkland tried to escape.
You had no choice
but to use deadly force.
Do you understand?
- Tiger tiger.